all right let's go back to the omen so
now we're talking about the the great
qualities of the Sangha some burgundy me
and then lenient its own lumber so you
know the five paths of evolution for a
Buddhist practitioner path of
accumulation you're making good karma
piling up good karma and the path of
accumulation starts when you have a
personal disaster okay a tragedy in your
life okay you lose your husband or your
mother dies in your arms or okay then
you get interested in Buddhism because
something bad happen in your life so
that's considered in Buddhism the
beginning of a spiritual career when you
have a problem serious problem then you
make good karma okay pile up good karma
and that's enough to get an explanation
of the pen from somebody that's the
second part second level of realization
someone teaches you emptiness in a clear
way simple way okay then you understand
it third part part of sin and you see
emptiness directly okay these all all
people go through this part sooner or
later everybody in the universe goes
through these slides bugs fish birds
people number four you get used to what
you saw and you use it on your husband
okay you use what you learned about
emptiness in your real life okay with
your work with your family okay
and then Nirvana is past number five you
reach nirvana you get so good at
understanding that the husband is coming
from you
that no one can make you upset
even if they try okay like your best
friend okay
they do their best to irritate you and
your night haha you know I know you're
coming from what I did last week okay
I'm not going to make that mistake again
I hate you therefore I will be nice here
look I'm kidding
got it okay so as a as sang that jewel
bubble cribbage a start with the lowest
possible which is so plump somebody on
the first part
the only good thing they ever did was to
have a tragedy and they got spiritual
okay so and Yentl Yenta means they
didn't learn the Bodhisattva teachings
here so he tried to pick as a Sangha
jewel the lowest possible person okay
you have to appreciate that so now if we
take them for an example see Paulo in
gym kami they get they get sad about
this life because they had a tragedy
okay
CIPA large engine engine makes me engine
same thing they they get sad about the
world you know if my mom can die in my
arms if - husband who loved me for so
many years can leave me suddenly
anything's possible
they get sad about life okay engine k9
so Dom the shoot day and that pushes
them into the first path okay charger
get salt choke some fella they increase
their practice of the 13 buddhist
component 13 parts of buddhism he calls
it - 13 parts of beauty & Chong's eg
totem of some Toba and they start on the
first three groups
of the Buddha quality okay so these are
two technical terms and I have to
explain them to you okay first one is
third team practices 13 ways to make
good karma that are happening on the
first path how did you get on the first
path
yeah personal tragedy so you gotta
figure out a personal tragedy then you
have 13 things to practice on the first
path these come from a Sangha okay
these come from a summer I'm going to go
straight to them you want to go deeper I
mean this lumber is going to take like
30 years it's okay if I do this it's
going to take longer it's okay I can we
didn't get very far in 25 three chains
but okay we bought so lunch editorship
allah let me tell you more about that
first path okay I got it for I went to
Jim John Bingham who lived in the 1200
and he wrote a very famous book called
Tim's ax which means Tim mr. Jim's
commentary to the abhidhamma kosher so
this is a be dumber okay and he's pretty
cool because he's before tsongkhapa he's
200 years before so couple so it's
unusual that so old that we follow it
very closely it's a big commentary to
abhidharma after Stanley translates the
long commentary on abhidharma
he's going to translate the longer
commentary and Aragon
I think he's scheduled to finish in 2022
that's why you have to choose young
transfers okay so he says that Tim
jumping on let me tell you more about
that first part okay Timmy me nam do
logic player go door lammle one of the
team will give a talk it is collecting
more and more good karma
before you can reach the second tab
which is preparation okay
preparation for what to see emptiness on
the third box okay second path is called
preparation that so the first path
definition make enough good karma to get
to the second path okay which is the
door to emptiness you see because the
third path is seeing emptiness directly
okay what it means is after you have
your personal tragedy you have to
collect enough good karma to have
somebody teach you the pen got it I
don't know why she didn't throw it to me
okay
so really the definition of the first
task is to just make enough good karma
until you meet someone who teaches you
the pen okay it doesn't have to be a pen
it could be anything could be a cell
phone you know I use cell phones too
nowadays more because kids don't use
pens nothing at all they don't need them
then I use them for anything WeChat
killed pens okay none of the generator
it's okay that's the definition of okay
it's the making enough good karma to
reach the door of emptiness which is a
second path which is where someone will
teach you pen okay sashimi cave
attendant La Nina there are two examples
one is called extraordinary first path
and one is called ordinary first path
okay Tobin in a double-knit Tonto
challenge a old nature pod euro the
first one is called helps you get the
freedom okay the exceptional form of
program the first time
is called type of chatter in fact that's
a definition
the technical definition is called topic
chatter chuckling means conducive to
tapa to freedom
moksha okay and he says I'm going to
explain that more later me pineal a
Tomoya talked a little bit go thinking
their guilt on Tinian day the second
kind of first time is where a person
tries to collect lots of good karma and
dedicated to reaching freedom freedom
normally means Nirvana
okay DRD needed soon a turd on Sunday
and a shippin and she may she naked na
minky party Shepherd on couldn't
literally so keel unconscionability
quotes some Achaia and he says what's
the definition of so clung so silky with
to tuned on the morality followed by a
person who has not yet seen emptiness is
first time
Wamba Kadamba they control their senses
they control their talking they control
their eating they control their
listening to rock and roll sort of I can
like take control there they don't have
too much sex they don't go crazy about
you see they control their senses it
doesn't mean you can't enjoy food it
doesn't mean you can't enjoy intimacy
with your partner it just means you
protect your senses you don't over load
them the circuits okay sake it's a
shepper a means to judge correctly serve
means the measure of your food to judge
correctly how much you should eat okay
it's about a third of what you eat now
okay you can say it's part of party huh
it's to carefully judge how much you eat
and bite by bite you know like six bites
okay seven bites two months okay by the
way part of taking refuge one of the
vowels of taking refuge is to thank the
Buddha's every day Buddhist Lamas
Bodhisattvas thank them every day by
offering the first part of your food
okay so before you drink a tea you go
you know you offer it then you drink
your tea okay some people forget to go I
[Music]
thought people they eat one by little Oh
No look forward to okay so in English we
call it grace grace has many meanings
the word grace has many meanings but in
English it can mean offering the first
part of your food offering the first
part of what you drink to your teacher
to the Buddha's to Bodhisattvas okay so
my Lama taught me many graces food
offering prayers Mohammed ought me many
of them and I took the my favorite six
and I put them in your meditation book
okay and we'll let's go over them now
quickly Center on the subject of food
this is before you eat and before you
drink okay even if you're just going to
have a cup of tea or a glass of water
then a Buddhist should first offer it to
their teacher or and it's a nice way to
show appreciation for your teacher or
for the Buddhist okay
there's a famous story of lama zopa
rinpoche that he does so many food
prayers he took a long flight
they offered food and he offered it so
long that they were landing and they
took that they took the food away from
him he didn't get to eat the food
because he was offering for like an hour
okay so don't do that but you can you
know offer okay if you're in a rush okay
I'll teach you the emergency offering
you just say oh okay
okay by the way some people say whom
it's not food it's not ate um that's a
mispronunciation hu ng who who like
French
oh boo boo boos mm-hmm oh ma okay oh ma
three times okay so even in super
emergency you can't just do one time
okay you can go oh my home oh it means
bless my body speech and mind okay
bless my body speech and mind um ah okay
so you do it three times
you know Oh mom if you're in a rush okay
if you're not in a rush you should
memorize these parents if you're
especially if you're learning to button
this is what they teach kids in the
monastery they teach them the Buddhist
grace so grace in English means food
offering it's on page 21 first ones on
page with 21 I'll give you a loom okay
I'll give you a loan oral brushing
tumble numbers from your rim bulging
your bone on my don't you remember your
number
remember governor going to some mojo
ball before then okay
I make offering to the three supreme
jewels to those who are my shelter
matchless teacher the press's Lord
Buddha mattress protection the precious
holy dharma matchless guides the
precious song okay that's basic food
offering okay everybody
learnt it okay you can memorize it in
English okay that's very very basic
everyone should know that one okay the
rest are optional this one you should
know you're taking refuge while you
offer you food right good a dumb
assembler okay so I called it a grace to
the three jewels okay
okay number two page 23 and 23 yeah this
is also very important you're offering
the food or the drink to your teacher
okay
could be lineage teachers Buddha negara
nor tsongkhapa it could be your mom or
your dad especially if your name is Tina
do you have a wonderful mom and dad and
you offer to them okay you offer the
food to them you offer the drink to them
because they are your teachers they are
your first teacher okay okay why should
we say
I'm okay
hang on one second I want to get the
pronunciation right
okay ready don't get them continued a
charm color conditioning too soon a
torrential muumuu due to the day
gentlemen I'm not your ball pool okay
and you can do it in your own language
okay you are my llama you are the keeper
of the diamond all three jewels in a
single person you take the form of my
human teacher you take any form it takes
to tame each one of us and by doing so
you grant us both highest and common
goals i make offering to my mama's you
are so kind to me okay the basic meaning
of the parents you are like an actor you
know you come into my life as my mother
or father you come into my mind fest
eacher you come into my life as my
partner you come into life as my
children and you teach me or my dog
Gracie and you can you teach me and
thank you for that okay that's the grace
okay got it
that's also important one they're all
important yeah okay grace number three
this is a try to make the Karma to have
good meditation okay generally food
doesn't work well with meditation but in
this prayer you are offering your food
and you are praying that everybody
should have a good meditation okay
ready here saloon shares our burgers
ever on YouTube on they don't even give
us a channel they paper word or deed
okay you don't even think about
okay this food has a thousand flavors
well made heart stealing I offer it in
faith to the victors and to their
dollars and sons by this act may every
living being
enjoy the richest feast of all perfect
meditations
okay so that's if you're having trouble
with your meditation eat as much as you
can and do this grace before I'm just
kidding
probably should eat less okay okay
who's the daughters and who's the
victors
yeah the virtus who's their daughters
and sons it's a name for body surface
okay so you're offering this food to
Buddha and the Buddha suffers and you
dedicating the Karma that other people
should enjoy the tasty french fry called
schemata
okay got it okay next one this is the
famous grace it's the oldest one and it
was written by Nagarjuna okay it's part
of one of the Guardian s books and it
came to be used as a grace okay okay he
talked about using food carefully and
that verse became a grace became a
famous grace so if you have trouble with
food causes you trouble like you can't
stop eating you can't control yourself
this is a good one okay if you if you
want to learn to think of food in the
proper way then you can do this Chris
okay and and the gardener's idea is you
should start to see food as fuel or as
medicine to keep yourself going it's
just to keep yourself going it's not to
make big muscles or
in India in ancient times there wasn't
enough food sometimes so people who are
a little bit fat were considered very
beautiful and same in Europe okay so the
gardener said don't eat to get handsome
or beautiful and don't eat to get big
muscles you know don't eat for your ego
eat for fuel just to keep your body
going enough to keep your body going
which is about a third of what you eat
now okay here we go
cotton and angelalivengood oh on me
button get a junction mallet maybe Jim
alex schulte mama minibus in church
don't do it for that don't do it for
that don't do it for that it's like that
okay Maalik not for that okay I will see
this food as medicine as fuel I can use
to destroy my desire and anger not to
look strong not to look beautiful not
for my ego but only to keep my body
going today okay that's the Gaggia miss
grace okay number fire this is our
prayer if you're a some copying people
ask me are you a Buddhist I'd say no I'm
not so copying it's a better okay this
is a grace to offer the food to Toccata
and his two main students Delta J and
okay this is Gail today and so copies
right and k2t on some compasses on and
that's so couple in a minute okay
so I'll read it to you contention day
Susan tsongkhapa don't be they want to
get oh gee don't let the mid-level
creativejourney go as gallery of Sisu
much above who okay and offering the
first part of your any meal also snacks
if you're American you can do a lot of
prayers
all day because every snack you can
offer make offering so it's smacking
because a great opportunity to make some
good karma we like to smack Americans
like this magnifique okay I make
offering to the victorious ones to the
father and his sons to some kapa
spiritual innovator here in the land of
snows to gallop G absolute Lord of logic
that reveals the truth and Takeda be a
great master of the open and secret
teachings okay so that's a prayer to
some companies to make disciples
everything you hear at Diamond Mountain
everything you hear in DCI everything
you hear in a CI everything you hear at
three jewels is it's because of these
three people
everything comes directly from this okay
we don't teach anything else okay we
have a Ferrari and we're not interested
in Volkswagens okay I mean sorry okay
okay the last one is a little bit secret
but I thought you guys are so serious
you come from so far away this is
actually tantric this is actually mod
Rihanna offering so if you have
initiations you can say it if you don't
have initiation so I give you permission
to say it and it will plant a seed to
get an initiation okay so this is a
grace to Jenga you do jumbled Jim can
you tumble
budget yogini angel is diamond okay and
it's a special grace to to her okay and
it's very sexy and it's very cool in
it's very beautiful okay run under you
know not always say duty Rolando Japan
Lord Asian conveyancers um oh oh nothing
calles sung-mo homies wow we're so lucky
okay hey Emma home Emily listen lucky
you know Emma home then making car song
is all I'm so lucky to be here you know
okay the last line is very cool Wow
I'm so lucky can we imagine cosmogony
the I then in the intensive practice you
see yourself as her okay you are
actually offering the food to yourself
I'm already Buddha
I'm this lady Buddha I'm a lady Buddha
that by the way in Buddhism that's the
highest Pune it's a lady Buddha okay so
long I'm the lady Buddha okay
I'm the protecting angel of what seems
on what is God okay of what seems and
what is gone we met these two today you
tell me who it is
she said the two husbands right did you
yeah she got it okay what is gone is
shopping okay it means empty no husband
like that it's gone never was there okay
got it
and what seems is the knick okay looks
like my husband that's dependent
origination what it's gone is emptiness
okay and and she she she's both this
angel is super cool she has 5050
emptiness and dependent origination okay
I savor this taste of this food as an
actor of deathlessness so she's not
eating calories
she's eating deathlessness a murder a
murder if you want to mispronounce
you can say Amrita okay say uh Mirta
amrita means to die very much okay
mirtha means to never die which one you
are
Murdoch okay yeah okay so by the way if
you're interested alberta means no death
right nectar which is the greek means
free from death neck means death
necrophilia and darken some color to
cross beyond so the Greek is the same
neck dark it means a Murtagh
it's the same word we call nectar and it
changed my mind
this food is not food it's nectar
deathless nectar and when I put it on my
tongue it goes damn and my mind goes
into emptiness you know like I ate a
French wine then my mind goes into
emptiness okay it's like that so when
you eat you like one two boom you know
then your mind doesn't you know it's a
prayer like that I hope that food gives
me that idea okay my god okay into the
empty realm which is combined with
highest bliss okay and that's secret I
can't tell you about them but you have
to learn it later okay
after long room he okay so those are six
Grace's you can do and practice them
during your three-day retreat you know
use them during a three-day retreat okay
like what mood in my end today I like to
pray for better meditation then do the
meditation grace okay today I'm sort of
feeling vain then do the Nicodemus grace
you see that means or I'm so grateful
for my teachers then do the teacher
grace okay
or I want the Karma to understand taking
refuge in the three jewels so then do
the three jewels grace okay but really
from now on you shouldn't eat without
some kind of grace okay you shouldn't
drink anything without something and you
see suggestion Michael he's like I'm
home you just emergency right just get
in the habit you know you watch any Lama
anywhere any good Lama than their like
so they're not talking to themselves
okay then they're doing a grace okay any
time now even a glass of water I don't
know about gum should we offer gum you
don't really eat it let's offer it
anyway
it's just another excuse of your prayer
okay
so learn to do them and practice them
during during this three-day retreat
okay okay and you know after a week you
should memorize them something you can
do that that can be part of your retreat
you could just learn your favorite one
by heart in your own language it's okay
you don't have to do into that and
you're not to bitten neither of mine
okay all right let's go back to the yeah
you're welcome I'm glad I had a reason
to share those Grace's to my teacher he
if I eat without that I get a blessing
okay he only hit me a future okay
nagi-chan third and Uncle Tom a lot me
Noah
this is another practice at the first
pass is get up early in the morning okay
just learn some people say I'm not a
morning person
well become a morning person
and go go to bed you know my llama goes
to bed at 8:30 or 9:00 o'clock you know
and then get up at 5:00 or something and
use those beautiful hours of the day
when the world is quiet okay before your
kids get up okay
use those beautiful times of the day so
go to bed early get up early you know
try to get in that habit you'll be much
much more productive also if if you just
want to be a business person or
something if you'd learn to get up early
you're much you much better you do much
better if you don't eat too much you can
get up early okay all right she's in the
Bloomberg Allah then take joy in your
life young hunger give the Jewish and
interpolate you want somebody to and
uncle aletan we shouldn't kill
relationship and try to go through the
practice of how Buddhists train
themselves is called to some gum say to
some gone to some gold this is Buddhist
education number one go to classes go to
classes go to classes over and over and
over
okay for many years I never missed my
teachers classes he taught the alphabet
ABC Kaka God and I went and I sat in the
back because I don't want to miss
anything you know and I'm really happy I
did that okay I never missed a class
then sometimes later I had to travel
during the diamond business and I would
miss some classes but don't miss a class
okay if you can help it - so that's
table means when you get home think
about what you learned and the one of
the best ways to do that is to talk it
over with your
France okay like when Dharma people get
together they should talk about what
happened at the last lamrim class don't
talk about Trump it's hopeless
okay don't waste your time then to talk
about what you learned in the class okay
don't talk about movies and don't talk
about you know the three irritating
Dharma students that come to every
program now you have to figure out
whether you're one of them okay and just
talk about Dharma and then go means of
course meditate on my tonight okay now
we got to the third this is the thirteen
okay this is the real 13 this is where I
got it from Kim jump in okay here we go
number one docked on Shin Jabba means
make it a practice to serve other people
you know I enjoy and I know I know other
people here do take care of older people
give rides to poor people visit people
in the prisons you know that kind of
stuff okay you're never too advanced to
do those practices like homeless people
okay like you're never so important that
you shouldn't make meals for sick people
or poor people or things like that okay
Goomba means aspire work hard okay chill
is a printing error it should be
touching keep your ten good deeds one
low means power I think it's similar in
Chinese language right one taller how do
you say Tom
Lee Jung nothing okay but there are five
there are five same as powers at the
first part okay
they are the following number one and
they're I think they're in a yoga sutra
or maybe not yeah I think they are yeah
shudder various smirky Samadhi and
prancin you're probably something like
that depa means safe safe okay believe
shut yeah should tender means enjoy
enjoy
hard practice okay enjoy your life enjoy
your practice okay Delia timba means
mindfulness okay like if you lose your
jumbo when you get a box of chocolates
you will eat all of them before you
remember what you're doing okay that's
called smarty memory remembering where
what you're doing don't do my listing
okay King in Zen is meditation in other
words for meditation somebody and shut
up is to think about emptiness as far as
you understand it that's number four of
the 13th all of those five is number
four okay number five
say again here it refers to eating
carefully okay learning to eat carefully
learning to eat carefully it takes many
years and some people never learn they
die before they learn to eat
it seems like eating shouldn't take any
knowledge but it takes a lot of
knowledge to eat properly okay menial
means don't ya don't oversleep you know
go to bed early get up early a little
early to bed early to rise makes a man
healthy wealthy in life okay
true patient you need chip Amin son keep
a mindfulness you know it means be
careful what you say to people be
careful what you do even when you're
tired even when you're busy
watch yourself and and are carefully
Gary Shannon means find a teacher and
serve them find a teacher and serve them
okay
serve the Dhamma take your time go slow
check many people you know and check out
the teacher before you go to their class
you know find out are they a good person
okay ask many people
check out that reputation see if there's
any problems okay scandals things like
that check about them are they honest
are they well trained
are they compassionate okay and then
help them because they're helping other
people right Dom Chen Yin means God
study the Dharma okay number 10 December
means think about what you learned
okay Karcham may means avoid things that
would be an obstacle okay one of the
biggest obstacles is stupid friends
okay my brother killed himself when he
was young he was 20 or 21 years old and
he met some bad young people he you know
and we were all nervous I felt very
nervous they were using guns they were
using drugs they were stealing things
and so one of the ways to avoid
obstacles in your life is be careful who
you hang out with be careful who you
make your friend okay choose your
friends wisely okay and if you choose
good friends you'll always be okay
they will take care of you you take care
of them you support each other
if you meet a person who's not kind not
compassionate not honest even if they're
very handsome are very beautiful or
something like that it's going to be
trouble in later okay something will go
wrong and they will hurt you okay it's
better to find a person who's not so
beautiful but they are honest and they
are clean and they have a good mind and
okay so don't look at the inside look at
the look at the inside and don't look at
the outside when you choose your friends
okay
choose good people okay mmm
don't want means be jealous okay
practice sharing what you have with
other okay and then gauge on again is
again means that jewelry and gauge on
means spiritual practice let your
jewelry be your spiritual practice
okay wear the jewelry of good daily
practice
keep a good guru practice okay those are
the third team that he mentioned okay
then he said the last three of the what
did he call it yeah he said the first
three groups but he didn't explain it
okay so I went and got it for you okay
and that's why we're going to go so slow
through this text so all the qualities
of a Buddha and needed to become a
Buddha okay that's an important
distinction are grouped into seven seven
famous groups okay a Buddha qualities
not because Brutus only have them but
because you need them become bliss okay
Buddha's have them in their highest form
so there are seven groups three of them
you can do on the first part okay
three of the seven groups of practices
you can do on the first pass okay so
here they are set can bar near sha Chi
combine your sexy okay so number one go
down on my bed should be a number one
keep going there you go right there
yeah Timmy yes I see so these are the
first of the seven famous groups of
Buddha qualities okay which again can be
called as that make you good okay and
it's a bad trend people translate it as
are you warm
are you okay you okay you okay
okay D let's make it democratic how many
people are air-conditioned you raise
your hand how many people don't want to
can you see me okay you win so there's a
bad English translation is close
recollections to foreclose recognitions
it's a ridiculous translation you never
go up to somebody and say I had a closer
recollection today you can say at a
close call with my wife
okay so I would just call it like I
don't know groove awarenesses the fourth
a four kinds of awareness okay people
get hung up on Sanskrit prefixes like if
they saw the word consciousness they
would say knowing together you see the
name they get anyway Bok dong Hong Kong
can make me numb she it's for its for
parts of Vipassana
it's for parts of Vipassana if you want
to butcher that word what can you call
it the personal okay that's a mistake
okay it's Vipassana touch means to see
there means very well the posh Jana is
is to is a deep meditation okay and by
the way it's not even a it's not
meditation it's a kind of understanding
the ten Vipassana understanding the ten
schemata deep meditation they always go
together so when you think the personal
is a meditation it's wrong already
you're already wrong okay all right then
you go deeper so anyway so Lou Germany
shot so Germany Luxembourg Germany
Russia and children Monisha okay these
are for awarenesses that you develop as
you start to understand emptiness okay
you want to go deeper
okay we'll never finish the turn the
first path has three levels in Sun the
first time that you reach by having a
personal tragedy okay there are three
levels inside the first path first one
is when you get these four kinds of
awareness okay that's the lowest one
okay and it has four parts number one
body about your body you learn to
examine how it's my arm like the pen how
is my arm like the pen okay if the arm
coming from my mind or is the arm coming
from the arm you see and you apply your
knowledge to the body okay
it's my I'm coming from me or is it
coming from my arm okay by the way it is
coming from me your life is dangerous
and your life is hopeful if your arm is
coming from your seats then your life is
dangerous and it's hopeful why is it
dangerous
your human seed can change the dog seeds
in five minutes and you can look at a
dog leg if it's coming from its own side
life is easier you can have an arm for a
while but if it's coming from your seeds
life is dangerous you can become a dog
garment into five minutes okay because
the dog arm also coming from you okay so
thinking about those things is a by the
way is hopeful because it can become
Buddha or muscle if you have Buddha
seeds it will become Buddhist on same
same thing like a pen okay go okay
do jumping jacks so uh same thing about
your feelings same thing about your
feelings it's more subtle it's more
difficult
what's the emptiness of your feelings
you know they they shift like the wind
right you're having a good time with
your partner
and then suddenly five minutes later
you're fighting you know and and that's
the emptiness of your feelings you see
they are also sprouting they are flowing
out of your seeds and they can shift
immediately and it's good seeds are
coming up the movie is good and if
dozens are coming up the movie is
terrible it's the same movie or music
okay or Dermot on how you feel about it
it's coming from your seeds okay if
that's the awareness of your feelings
okay that's the second of this form okay
third one Santa by yourself
even the thoughts I hear in my mind are
coming out of my seat I am just the
witness I am just listening - Karma's
opening okay I don't like him he's not
nice he didn't say hi to me before the
Klan okay that whiny voice in your mind
it's coming out of your seeds okay it's
because you said like that to other
people last week okay so you have karma
to hear this person complaining inside
your mind okay got it
that's the emptiness awareness of your
own songs
okay and now church elder man your shot
means everything all things the world
around you the people you meet the
weather the traffic everything keep this
awareness that it's coming from your
seats okay all right if you mastered
those four you can say you'll finish the
first third of the lowest part okay why
are we talking about this we're talking
about the lowest example of Sangha jewel
now it's beginning to sound a little bit
higher okay
they've they've mastered all these
things okay
second group is called Yom Kippur
washing these are very famous for its
another four and I think the total of
the seven groups is 37 and they're
called us the 37 limbs of a nightmare so
again looking so second group is for
what part of the first path - they
relate care yeah
the middle part the second part begun it
don't get confused where we are I know
you're confused okay I don't care those
with jet lag are marker few I love it
because I I'm always jet lag in your
country now you're just like in my
country okay now that Balaji means for
it got rid of four things or something
like that
the four ways that you got rid of
something okay young by polishing the
four ways that you got rid of something
very well young bar or watching okay
here they are number one
Miguel get bipolar any bad habits you
have you get rid of them any bad habits
you had already you get rid of them
that's number one number two me give up
my kid let me give up any bad habits you
might have next year you get rid of them
this year
okay future bad habits future bad see
you get rid of them now you stop them
now stop the ones that grew already and
stop the ones that are on their way
it's the first tooth got it you alright
if you're totally lost just nod yeah
okay just 9
okay okay third one gara gara my can't I
give up try to make good seeds that you
haven't got yet okay like try to make
new kinds of good seats try to make new
kinds of good seats
it's number two now yeah it's called got
rid of that it's not okay I'm sorry
only the first one is I didn't make the
list Buddha made the list you can write
a letter to to schita okay just put your
on the letter let's see what
happens okay get my kpop Pella Gaelic
epic Bella means the good seeds you've
already have try to feed them try to
make them bigger okay so on means this
spell means to make it bigger
okay so I'll summarize those four that
happen at the middle part of the first
path okay ready
the bad seed you already have try to get
rid of the bad habit number one number
two the new bad habits you haven't
developed yet don't develop them okay
like I have a problem with jealousy but
I don't have a problem with alcohol okay
so for me number one would be try to get
rid of your old bad habit Michael of
jealousy okay number two would be don't
start the new alcohol bad habit that you
don't have yet okay it's it's on the
short list of things I didn't do wrong
in my life okay
number 30 Jeremih kippa kippa if there's
some good habits you don't have you I
try to get them I don't know like
helping homeless people and number four
if you're already helping homeless
people try to expand your operation
okay the United States I mean it's
nothing let's get to Mexico you know
when I see something happening in Canada
you know okay all right okay those are
the second group got it and therefore
the middle of the first pass now let's
go to the third group and you'll be
totally confused then I'll give you a
little break okay then I'll give you a
10-minute break okay so I know the jet
lag is this is where the DCI stuff
starts newsing in their chair they've
learned to do this in their chair you
know Scott you say he learned to sleep
in the class with his eyes with his eyes
open antenna or read is more advanced if
I say everybody understands he's like
exactly it's me from jet lag
Scott can't do that he's just like
aretha okay uh your to accomplish it
these are difficult these it's hard to
get a good explanation of these the
seven parts of a Buddha okay jus chill
means uh the ability to do miracles
we had another word for it earlier today
called shuttle same thing do to your
children children
there's a famous holiday called children
guichen the day of miracles okay so do
ii mean miracle tomba means your legs so
it's the for miracle legs okay the four
legs of miracles and then you know
people make pretty weird translations
like oh your your legs are so miraculous
you know okay
birds I got it what's about Mexico City
people are so smart I don't know okay
that even collar city mexico city called
Mexico okay the main thing is employee
digit and damage it incumbent on
singleton engine pollutant and damage
duty to come and saluting at some point
did you get with the recommended tippet
engineer are going oh my gosh twine
artifact so you get these at the third
part of some of the first pass and
generating engine purring depicting into
employment routine and damage so to come
but I got a look at up for you I'm not
happy with this let me do it later I'll
do it tomorrow
I looked it up but I don't like it I
don't like it
okay alright
I promised you a break after that okay
[Music]
let's do a question/answer let's have
fun for 20 minutes okay any question and
answers we need a microphone no Jenny
had one not have a single border Thank
You Fisher case now we'll talk about the
pain the last one the number 13 I just
want to come from 0 where the jewelry
and you do the practice every day is
like this meaning the jewelry that you
wear yeah is your practice okay there's
no physical jewelry ah just metaphor
okay thank you but if you want to wear
jewelry and practice it okay what's the
khamar of a desirable food come up with
desire for food too much oh yeah yeah
yeah I don't know if I knew I wouldn't
have a problem myself
uh I I think part of it might be sharing
bad food with other people you know like
giving people your job you know get
instead of vegetables you know like I
think part of the bad karma of having a
food problem might be that we we don't
help other people to eat good food we
give them it's very common in America
and I was brought up in America to give
someone bad food as a gift like
chocolate or a cake or you see many
people give me box of chocolate you know
and finally I learned to throw them out
in the airport after I go through
customs
you know I said goodbye everybody thank
you for the chocolate and then finally I
learned when I go through the passport
on the other side I throw it out
you know so maybe part of that karma is
encouraging other people to eat bad food
I think like give in America if you like
somebody you make them a cake or you
make them a pie and it hurts them really
you're hurting them diabetes is very
serious and many people die from
diabetes I think it's number three cause
of death and you get it from eating
those things so I think maybe we need a
culture where when you give a gift of
food you give something healthy
character anyway that's my that time
thinking right now
Vivien Harmon and luxury in short take a
moment Ron Johnson so tenacious don't
eat em Cheech & Chong's 1100 ocean now
can you take issue where chances are
sushi yo : kinda Kyoko Joshua
Mishima show conscience
Natasha member tomcee eating su Chi Yeol
appearance a poutine commercial petrol
go over to Charles Eagle investor Ho Oh
muchos de ellos pero mejor no Tom
cheetah Dalmatian muhandojeon lagoon you
can do Rihan goodness
you lie you told us that 90% of the sea
is your motivation and you also said the
way we we get the desire for might be
sharing that food with other people but
what if we share the password with good
motivation yeah I think most people do
which is probably why you're still alive
so I yeah I mean nobody gives somebody a
yo table and say I hope it kills you you
know so it's true
90% is motivation so maybe in many cases
of the 10% it caused the desire for food
I think the parents especially have to
be more careful I was in a bookstore and
a family came in man and his wife and a
small small town and they went to the
bookstore coffee shops and they bought a
chocolate chip cookie like this my dad
and they gave the whole thing to a small
town and they ate it and then like half
an hour later the kids start screaming
crying fighting and the parents are like
hitting him and I'm like you we should
hit you you you gather it's too much
sugar for force like this they gave them
in ten minutes and so I think parents
also have to be careful it's not nice to
give to teach your kids if you are good
I will give you shivers see you're
hurting them you know
in America it's all like that sugar
thing more important than the dollar you
cold
thanks for the opportunity to ask
questions so when you when you reach
schemata and you have the seeds that
have the direct perception of emptiness
are you like are you having a
dissolution that's similar that happens
at the time of death is there something
happening with the withdrawal of that
consciousness is it similar or is it
different or is there a stopping of the
breath I would like if you could talk a
little bit more about the difference
between those two processes good
questions I think you've heard me say
many times according to Scripture when
you see emptiness directly your central
channel opens completely and that's the
physical cause to see emptiness directly
and in Buddhism the purpose of yoga is
to help the central channel to open
completely the purpose of yoga is to see
emptiness the purpose why we do yoga
every day is to it helps you to get the
Chi into the central channel and that
that causes you to see emptiness
directly so yoga in Buddhism is an
important practice for your life for in
our group in our immediate group it
contributes to what you learned in this
in this class it supports what you
learned in the class if you do yoga
regularly and I don't mean this standing
on one hand
okay that's fun if you can do it it's
fun I like it but a just a regular
gentle good stretch you know the
practice everyday not like super Anatole
okay just Pleasant stretching some good
cardiac things it helps your central
channel open if the central channel
opens you see emptiness directly the
central channel opens two times
naturally during your life one is during
orgasm when you have a sexual orgasm for
a few seconds just for a few seconds
uncontrollably right your central
channel opens and and then when you die
at that point that we talked about the
Crystal point your central channel also
opens for brief periods and so in in the
natural flow of life and death your
central channel opens during those two
circumstances and I have a theory that
the reason people are so attracted to
sex
I mean obsessed with sex almost
everybody sections the most common word
looked up on the internet for example by
a lot I think it's the craving for
seeing emptiness you see I think they
are connected subconsciously people
don't understand it they're driven by
that urge but they don't understand that
maybe it's a spiritual instinct you know
that gets made commerce or low but it's
this so that the desire to have this
central channel wins slow I think it's a
high thing and you can use it for that
you should use it for that
that's all is that your question I was
asking about well thank you for that
answer I was asking about it like during
the direct perception of emptiness is
there a dissolution process and is there
a caballo kombucha that occurs or
something
I'm just curious yo yeah yeah the
opening of the central channel during
the direct possession of emptiness is
exactly the same as the opening of the
central channel for a few seconds during
orgasm and exactly the same as the
opening of the central channel for 5-10
minutes as you die same same opening I
wouldn't call the dissolution I don't
think they would call it a dissolution
but the result or the final stage of it
is too soon yeah but one is done with
control and one is done you know sort of
like a beast you know
it just happens you know you don't know
what's happening the two are the first
two the direct perception of emptiness
and orgasm are more pleasant whereas
like recent for your areas recession
emptiness is much more so you can't
really be having a fear at that time of
because you're at a platform of physical
and mental fluency that's very blissful
right in the direct perception of
emptiness so you can't be if you're if
it opens it's not like you know no
there's no fear is an unchanging thing
and the object of the sentence here is
not ultimate reality during that
experience it's impossible to perceive
any existing entity which is not
ultimate reality you can't be aware of
fear you can't be aware of joy you can't
be aware of your own mind you can't be
aware of yourself you are just to let
your chakra water poured into water your
mind is an emptiness so
there can't be any other emotions on
then you would pop out because that's
ultimate rioni
does the first stop are Kerala kumbhaka
right the spontaneous suspension of
breath is a very common indication that
you are close to seeing emptiness
directly so what the Yogi's call kevala
khumba car which is the spontaneous
suspension of your breath for 5 minutes
10 minutes half an hour is it's a sign
that you're close yes
so if you get really close you might
notice you haven't breathed for 10
minutes or something which is an
interesting thing because that implies
that life is being sustained not by
oxygen but by karma and maybe breath is
not necessary you see and that makes
sense so it's a it's very interesting
that in the yoga scriptures they
discussed that kevin laka booka and then
they try to use physical means to induce
it you know like you know and I think
that's a tremendous mistake
I think that's can only give you lung
and can only cause your problems and I
don't think it has any benefit at all I
know some yoga schools where you try to
hold your breath first
that's like I don't know I don't know
it's like trying to have an orgasm by
eating cookies or something it's just
with no connection I mean maybe
otherwise no I mean it to me is it's it
can be a very harmful I know people have
had serious physical problems from China
hold their breath for three minutes
because they think it's a big yoga thing
when when you when your best starts it's
because of constant practice of kindness
and goodness in study and meditation
it's not that you force yourself to stop
you know it just stops okay yeah thank
you yeah yeah I just wanted to add a
question when can you see the emptiness
I want to seem too much directly on your
cushion or when you see emptiness
directly through the death process I
mean you're seeing the same emptiness
right you're seeing the emptiness of
your subject state of mind yeah it's a
good question there's only one emptiness
right so now you may not recognize it
and you know or you come close and you
don't know what's going on and you just
slit slide by and you become an animal
or some that's what happens most of time
so could you say that
on seeing emptiness on your cushion is
more reliant on an intellectual
understanding whereas sing it on your
death that is more reliant on repeating
that visualization over and over
rectangle you can say that yeah exactly
that's a good way to say yeah even I
mean animals have done bugs have done
they they slide by emptiness for a few
minutes or seconds during their death
and but they don't know what to do yeah
okay another question okay you got a
bright draw the night before
Elizabeta think you can so so much for
teaching us so you said to avoid
obstacles and like to the people and
people who can harm you so this is
something I've struggled with since I
got into Dharma if everyone is coming
from me and if the seeds ripen every 24
hours I feel like by avoiding people who
can harm me I'm trying to avoid the bad
karma and it may continue to ripen and
come back at me with even worse
senses could you explain the difference
when you avoid and when you take
responsibility for that karma and you
work on it okay good I think the purpose
to avoid someone is that you're not
strong enough to not be influenced by
them you see I mean if you're strong
enough you can hang around with bad
people because you will help them right
if you're not strong enough they will
influence your annual change so it kind
of depends on how strong you are you
know if you're really strong you can
hang out with you know be honest I was
in the diamond business for 19 years
many diamond people are dishonest you
know and when I was going to go work in
the diamond business I asked my mama I'm
afraid to go to the diamond business
because I'm afraid I will become like
toasty people he said no you strong
enough you know you're not gonna start
smuggling diamonds and and cheating
people with glass and you know cheating
on your taxes and you know it's not
going to don't worry
so I would say that if you're strong
enough you can put yourself into
situations where you're surrounded by
bad examples because maybe you can help
them become good examples but if you're
not strong enough they will change you
and sometimes we fool ourselves
oh I'm strong enough but then three
years later we're lying all the time
something like that I mean so you got to
be careful who you choose also I would
say who's your real friends you say I
mean we all have a close circle of
personal friends who are in English we
say confidant
you know we tell them all our secrets
they tell us all their secrets
especially those people should be good
people
so don't choose them on the basis of
their appearance don't choose them on
the basis of their income don't choose
them on the basis of their social level
sometimes people look there's a thing
where we we often feel that beautiful
people are more good somehow and it's
not correct you know you you you may
find out that the best people are not
the ones that look like George Clooney
you know although I think he's kind of
cool and his wife who's very beautiful
is an extremely good person and she's
helping many many refugees she's
extremely active and in dangerous
situations helping the refugees in Syria
so I think and in Lebanon so I think she
don't assume that people who look
angelic are angelic sometimes it's there
other people say I mean so judge who's
your close friends carefully and I they
had a rule I played tennis in high
school I wasn't that good I barely made
the team on some last fundamental team
and during the tennis season my coach
had a rule that we were not a play
allowed to play a match with anyone who
wasn't better than us you see we were
required to only play with other players
who could beat us regularly you see I
mean and I think your friends should be
the same like pick these high-quality
super honest you know super sweet good
example people and get close to them
even if you don't feel close to them in
the beginning try to get close to them
as you're close friends and then of
course you're teaching a lot you and
Anton are teaching a lot you should
reach out to people who are
you know bad business people rich guys
cheating lots of people you should try
to hang out with them and try to
influence them that's a good thing but
your your close personal friends I'd say
be really cheesy and pinky and China
hang out with people who are better than
you okay one more but if you don't have
I'll go to bed
Joel's choosing not me
look Buddhist fight he's trying to give
it to the other person a Buddhist fight
thank you one I appreciate that thank
you guys for teaching I've been thinking
I've been thinking a lot about
purification lately and so kind of
briefly I was taking a walk through that
down the very river went about two hours
in two hours out so on the way back out
I was walking through a clearing and I
saw a tree and I said to myself oh I
recognized that tree and I thought and
then all of a sudden I realized I've
never seen that tree before because I'd
never saw the back of the tree on the
way in but my mind had created a memory
of the back of the tree and then I was
like oh I'm not actually looking at
anything and ever saw it was never there
to begin with so so started thinking
about that in terms of negative seeds or
even positive sees where if I did
something in the past in that moment I
had a I know I planted some you know I
saw the complete thing happened but I
never saw that say the back side of of
that right so in purification if I had
that kind of view
then that negative seed almost doesn't
have that power that it may have had
before because I'm recognizing that I
never actually the other half of it
wasn't even there like if I'm
disappointing percentages on it and I'm
wondering that's a helpful way of seeing
that or that's sort of what kind of
happens in purification because I'm not
quite clear on how does one purify
negative seeds my answer is with one of
the meditations
it's
[Music]
where are you
number 11 okay
meditation number let's knock that out
since you brought it up okay the vulgar
impetus says protection is retroactive
okay so it means that if you did some
this a guy with the umbrella okay if you
planted a bad seed in the past and then
now you take refuge by thinking about
the second husband right it it damages
other branches it infects the other
branches the habit of thinking about the
pen damages old bouncies okay so
definitely if you start thinking about
the pen if you start thinking about
where things really come from it it
damages the seeds you planted ten years
ago when you hurt somebody
okay it's very interesting so taking
refuge now in the proper way can protect
you some things that were supposed to
happen to you because of something you
did ten years ago
that you're not even thinking about cool
it's like that so I think you're right
yeah if you do a good purification it
can it infects the other Betsey's in
terms of the Wheel of Life the eighth
and ninth links are called are called
desire and they shall desire an advanced
designer
the guy eating a big McDonald's dinner
and the monkey wreaking out fire on the
branch for some fruits those two they
trigger number 10 which is a right Karma
they make karma right and they involve
misunderstanding the scene so what's
interesting about karmic seeds is the
more you understand them the more you
damage the negative ones and you
reinforce the good ones it's interesting
it's called scorching in Buddhism it's
called scorching understanding seeds
scorches bad ones and renders them
impotence it's very interesting the more
you understand the way seeds work the
more you damage bad seeds just by
understanding them okay the best way to
damage the seed is to understand it cool
some like that all right